Finding Aid for the Lillian Faderman papers LSC.1849
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lillian Faderman papers
1976-1989
UCLA Library Special Collections
Faderman, Lillian
LSC.1849
8 oversize_boxes
Faderman's papers consist of drafts of her published papers and book reviews and manuscript and typescript versions of three of her books: Surpassing the Love of Men (1981); Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers (1991) and Chloe Plus Olivia (1994). The papers also include background research for her various publications; correspondence relating to her publications and speaking engagements; publicity materials and lesbian, gay and women's publications produced by now defunct small presses and various organizations.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lillian Faderman, 1991.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9964130693606533
Biography
Lillian Faderman is an internationally-known literary scholar and historian of lesbian history. She has published nine books and numerous articles on lesbian history, literature and criticism, including Surpassing the Love of Men (1981), an acclaimed study of five centuries of love between women, and Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers (1991), a history of twentieth-century lesbians in America, which were both named among The New York Times notable books of the year; her memoir, Naked in the Promised Land (2003) and her latest book, Gay L.A. (2006), which she co-authored with Stuart Timmons.
Faderman's work has centered on establishing a lesbian tradition, on what she calls a "usable past." In her early works, especially in Surpassing the Love of Men and Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers, she showed that so-called romantic friendships between women were considered neither abnormal nor undesirable in prior centuries. Accordingly, women who loved women in the past were not always made to live like outlaws. Only after 1980, in the aftermath of sexology, did same-sex love between women come to be seen as suspect, degenerate or even criminal. Faderman has also written on the theme of same-sex love and romantic friendship in poems and letters of Emily Dickenson; in novels by Henry James, Oliver Wendell Holmes, and Henry Wadsworth Longfellow and in popular magazine fiction of the early twentieth century.
Faderman's later book, To Believe in Woman: What Lesbians Have Done for America–A History (1999) is the culmination of her two previous books, Surpassing the Love of Men and Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers. It charts romantic friendships between women and lesbian love through some of the most important social movements in the U.S. and shows how these same-sex partnerships made major feminist causes of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries possible.
Faderman's other major books, each groundbreaking when it was published, are Lesbians in Germany (1980), her first work in lesbian history; Scotch Verdict (1983), which chronicles the 1810 trial of two Scottish schoolteachers accused of lesbianism; Chloe Plus Olivia (1994), an anthology of lesbian literature since the seventeenth century and I Begin My Life All Over: The Hmong and the American Immigrant Experience (1998), which records the story of 36 Hmong immigrants to California. Her articles on lesbian life and literature have appeared in diverse academic, feminist and lesbian journals, including The New England Quarterly, The Massachusetts Review, Journal of Popular Culture, Higginson Journal, Journal of Homosexuality, Signs, Conditions and Gay Books Bibliography.
Faderman was born July 18, 1940 in the Bronx, New York, the daughter of a single working mother who lost most of her family in the Holocaust. Throughout her childhood, Faderman's dream was to become a movie star. Faderman's family moved to east L.A. when she was a teen and she later attended U.C. Berkeley, where she worked as a burlesque stripper to support herself. She received a B.A. in English literature from U.C. Berkeley in 1962, an M.A. in English from UCLA in 1964, and a Ph.D. in English from UCLA in 1967. In 1967, Faderman started teaching in the English department at California State University, Fresno, where she began her career co-editing two anthologies of American multi-ethnic literature: Speaking for Ourselves: American Ethnic Writing (1969; 1975) and From the Barrio: A Chicano Anthology (1973).
Faderman served in various administrative positions (1971-1976) at California State University, Fresno, including Chair of the English Department, Acting Dean of the School of Humanities and Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs and then decided she preferred teaching and writing. Faderman, along with Phyllis Irwin, helped establish the first women's study program at California State University, Fresno in 1972. She was promoted to full Professor of English in 1973. Irwin later became her domestic partner of 40 years. They have one child: Avrom (1975- ).
Throughout her career, Faderman has been sought after as a speaker, teacher, critic, and visiting lecturer. Faderman has been a frequent speaker at lesbian and feminist organizations, universities, and lesbian, gay and women's organizations nationally and internationally, including the Modern Language Association (MLA), the National Women's Studies Association (NWSA), GAU (Gay Academic Union) and the Berkshire Women's History Conference.
Faderman's work has been translated into numerous languages, including German, Spanish, Italian, Japanese, Turkish, Czech, and Slovenian. Among her many honors are six Lambda Literary Awards, two American Library Association Awards, and several lifetime achievement awards for scholarship, including Yale University's James Brudner Award, the Monette/Horwitz Award, the Publishing Triangle Award, the ONE National Gay and Lesbian Archives Culture Hero Award, and the American Association of University Women's Distinguished Senior Scholar Award. She divides her time between Fresno and San Diego.
Chronology
Missing Title
1940 Born July 18, Bronx, NY.
1962 Received B.A. in English Literature from U.C. Berkeley.
1964 Received M.A. in English from UCLA.
1967 Received Ph.D. in English from UCLA.
1967 - Present Started teaching in the English department at California State University, Fresno.
1969 Co-edited Speaking for Ourselves: American Ethnic Writing
1971 - 1976 Served in various administrative positions at California State University, Fresno, including Chair of the Department of English, Acting Dean of the School of Humanities, and Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs.
1973 Co-edited From the Barrio: A Chicano Anthology
1973 Promoted to full Professor of English California State University, Fresno.
1980 Co-authored Lesbians in Germany, first book on a lesbian topic
1981 Published Surpassing the Love of Men: Romantic Friendship and Love Between Women from the 16th Century to the Present.
1983 Published Scotch Verdict
1991 Published Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers
1994 Published Chloe Plus Olivia
1998 Published I Begin My Life All Over: The Hmong and the American Immigrant Experience.
1999 Published To Believe in Woman: What Lesbians Have Done for America-A History
2003 Published Naked in the Promised Land
2006 Co-published Gay L.A.: A History of Sexual Outlaws, Power, Politics and Lipstick Lesbians with Stuart Timmons
Scope and Content
The Lillian Faderman papers document the internationally acclaimed lesbian historian's professional life. Papers date from 1975-1994, with the majority spanning the period 1979-1989. Among the papers are drafts of her published papers and book reviews and manuscript drafts of three of her books; correspondence, publicity materials, background research, contracts and royalty statements, printed matter, photographs and audio materials.
Publications, 1981-1994 (Series 1, Boxes 1-13), include drafts of Faderman's published papers and book reviews and manuscript drafts of three of her books: Surpassing the Love of Men (1981), an acclaimed study of five centuries of love between women; Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers (1991), a history of twentieth-century lesbians in America and Chloe Plus Olivia (1994), an anthology of lesbian literature since the seventeenth century.
Correspondence, 1979-1989 and undated (Series 2, Boxes 14-17), is with individuals; agents and publishers and institutions and organizations and concerns awards and prizes; the editorial process for Surpassing the Love of Men, including Faderman's choice of a commercial New York publisher; requests for reviews, speaking engagements and for Faderman's participation in programs or events; fan mail; legal matters, including foreign subsidiary rights and research files. Also included are letters and cards from Faderman's friends and a photograph of Phyllis Irwin, Faderman's domestic partner.
Printed Matter, 1975-1990 (Series 3, Box 18 and oversized boxes 19-27) includes newsletters, periodicals and newspapers of various lesbian, gay and women's organizations and groups and now defunct small presses.
Audio Materials, 1980-1981 (Series 4, Box 18) consists of both taped materials and compact discs covering interviews by Faderman with Barbara Gittings, an early pioneer lesbian activist, and Mariana Romo-Carmona, a Latina lesbian artist from New York City, for Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Series 1. Publications, 1981-1994. Boxes 1-13
Series 2. Correspondence, 1979 - 1989, n.d.. Boxes 14-17
Series 3. Printed matter, 1975-1990. Box 18 and oversized boxes 19-26
Series 4. Audio materials, 1987, Oct.. Box 18
Related Material
This collection forms part of the The June L. Mazer Archive at UCLA.
Faderman, Lillian
- Publications, 1981-1994; Series 1.; Boxes 1-13
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains manuscript and typescript drafts of various publications by Faderman. The largest section of files includes the manuscript drafts and galley proofs of three books written by Faderman: Surpassing the Love of Men: (1981); Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers (1991) and Chloe Plus Olivia (1994). There are also drafts of published papers and book reviews written by Faderman and prospectuses and outlines for forthcoming publications.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by folder label or chronologically by date.
  - Surpassing the Love of Men, 1981; Subseries 1.; Boxes 1-9
    - Completed manuscript draft of Surpassing the Love of Men, 1981; 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Surpassing the Love of Men uncorrected galley proofs with edits, 1981; 11 folders (Box 2)
    - Surpassing the Love of Men uncorrected galley proofs with edits, 1981; 6 folders (Box 3)
      General note
      Contains Start - Pg. 96; see Box 4 for Pg. 97 to end.
    - Surpassing the Love of Men uncorrected galley proofs with edits, 1981; 6 folders (Box 4)
      Contains Pg. 97 to end; see Box 3 for Start - Pg. 96.
    - Surpassing the Love of Men uncorrected galley proofs with edits (most recent draft), 1981; 6 folders (Box 5)
      Contains Start to Pg. 265; see Box 6 for Pg. 266 to end.
    - Surpassing the Love of Men uncorrected galley proofs with edits (most recent draft), 1981; 6 folders (Box 6)
      Contains Pg. 266 to end. See Box 5 for start to Pg. 265.
    - Surpassing the Love of Men corrected galley proofs, 1981; 10 folders (Box 7)
      Contains Start - Pg. 233; see Box 8 for Pg. 234 - end.
    - Surpassing the Love of Men corrected galley proofs, 1981; 11 folders (Box 8)
      Contains Pg. 234 - end; see Box 7 for start to pg. 233.
    - Surpassing the Love of Men master galley proofs, 1981; 11 folders (Box 9)
      Includes artwork and typescript.
  - Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers, 1991; Subseries 2.; Box 10
    - Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers uncorrected proofs, 1991; 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Other publications, 1979-1987; Subseries 3.; Box 11
    Alphabetical by folder label and then chronological by date.
    - Prospectuses and outlines, 1979-1987; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Proposed publications include Surpassing the Love of Men (1981); Love Between Women in the Twentieth Century and Women and War: History and the Present.
    - Published papers and book reviews, 1979-1987; 13 folders (Box 11, Folder 2 - 14)
      Drafts of published papers and book reviews written by Faderman, including articles on the theme of same-sex love and romantic friendship in poems and letters of Emily Dickenson; in novels by Henry James, Oliver Wendell Holmes, and Henry Wadsworth Longfellow; and in popular magazine fiction of the early twentieth century. Also includes Faderman's publications on the Scottish schoolmistresses whose lesbian libel suit inspired Lillian Hellman's The Children's Hour and led to the publication of Faderman's Scotch Verdict.
  - Chloe Plus Olivia, 1994; Subseries 4.; Boxes 12-13
    - Completed manuscript draft of Chloe Plus Olivia, 1994; 7 folders (Box 12, Folder 1 - 7)
      Start - Pg. 657. See Box 13 for Pg. 658 - End.
    - Completed manuscript draft of Chloe Plus Olivia, 1994; 5 folders (Box 13, Folder 1 - 5)
      Pg. 658 - End. See Box 12 for Start - Pg. 657.
- Correspondence, 1979 - 1989, n.d.; Series 2.; Boxes 14-17
  Contains correspondence and memoranda, contracts and publicity materials related to Faderman's publications and speaking engagements. The materials also include some information on foreign subsidiary rights relating to Surpassing the Love of Men and Scotch Verdict and permissions for various publications by Faderman to be reprinted.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title, and then chronologically by date.
  - Awards correspondence, 1982-1983; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Correspondence and memoranda related to awards and honorary degrees conferred, including the 1982 Gay Academic Union (GAU) "Literature Award", the 1982-83 California State University, Fresno (CSUF) "Distinguished Professor" award and the 1982 American Library Association (ALA) Gay Task Force's "Gay Book Award."
  - Fan mail, 1977-1988; 10 folders (Box 14, Folder 2 - 11)
    Fan mail consists of letters, postcards and greeting cards and contains general letters and specific ones lauding Surpassing the Love of Men, Scotch Verdict and other publications. Correspondents are individuals, including personal friends, women's studies professors, colleagues, teachers, students, politicians, editors and activists.
    Correspondence related to awards and honorary degrees conferred, including the 1982 Gay Academic Union (GAU) "Literature Award", the 1982-83 California State University, Fresno (CSUF) "Distinguished Professor" award and the 1982 American Library Association (ALA) Gay Task Force's "Gay Book Award," was removed and placed in the Awards Correspondence folder (also in Box 14).
  - Correspondence relating to Surpassing the Love of Men and Scotch Verdict, 1978-1989; 9 folders (Box 15, Folder 1 - 9)
    Correspondence and memoranda concerning the editorial process for Surpassing the Love of Men and Scotch Verdict. Correspondence is with agents, publishers and editors and concerns contracts, royalty statements, subsidiary rights and permissions, translations, editorial changes and publicity.
  - Correspondence relating to published papers and book reviews, 1976-1989; 10 folders (Box 16, Folder 8 - 17)
    Consists mainly of proposed submissions for articles and book reviews and for speaking engagements; calls for papers and requests to write and review.
    See Box 11 for related published papers and book reviews. Folder series originally labelled Acceptances, Rejections and Requests to Write and Review.
  - Correspondence relating to editorial boards and requests to write/review, 1979-1989; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Consists mainly of requests for Faderman's participation on editorial boards and panels.
  - Correspondence relating to speaking engagements and publicity materials, 1976-1987; 6 folders (Box 16, Folder 2 - 7)
    Requests for Faderman's participation in conferences, programs and events and as visiting lecturer. Publicity materials concern Surpassing the Love of Men and Scotch Verdict and include press announcements, book reviews and clippings.
  - Other correspondence, 1976-1989; 10 folders (Box 17, Folder 1 - 10)
    Contains a mixture of personal and professional correspondence that is not related to the editorial process for Faderman's publications. Correspondence concerns Faderman's speaking engagements, research relating to her publications and to lesbian and women's studies and requests for reviewers. Publicity materials and ephemera relating to Faderman's publications and to lesbian and women's publishing are also included here. Correspondents include various lesbian, gay and women's groups and publications, institutions and organizations and various individuals. The most noteworthy of these include Barbara Grier, Barbara Gittings, and Phyllis Irwin. Also of interest is the Judith Schwarz/Jonathan Katz correspondence which explains the issues surrounding Faderman's choice of a commercial publisher (William Morrow) for Surpassing the Love of Men.
    Folder 8 includes a photograph of Phyllis Irwin, Faderman's domestic partner, from Taos, 1987.
- Printed matter, 1975-1990; Series 3.; Box 18 and oversized boxes 19-26
  Contains newspapers, newsletters and periodicals by now defunct small presses and various lesbian, gay and women's organizations that do not include works written by Faderman.
  Chronological by Date of Publication.
  - Newsletters and periodicals, 1975-1988; Subseries 1.; Box 18
    Publications produced by now defunct small presses and various lesbian, gay and women's organizations and groups that do not include works written by Faderman.
    - Gay Life Magazine (St. Louis, MO), 1979, Feb - March; 2 issues [no.3 (Feb); no.4(March)] (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Gay Literature (Fresno, CA), 1975; 3 issues [Winter 1975 (no.1), Spring 1975 (no.2), Fall 1975 (no. 4)] (Box 18, Folder 10 - 12)
    - Gay Teachers Association Newsletter (New York City, NY), 1978-1982; 3 folders (Box 18, Folder 13 - 15)
      Vol. 1 no.1(January 1978) - no. 10 (December 1978); Vol. 2 no.1 (January 1979) - Vol. 2 no. 10(December 1979), special Gay Pride (March issue); Vol. 3 no. 1 (January 1980) - Vol. 3 no. 7/8 (September/ October); Vol. 3 no. 10 (December 1980) - Vol. 4 no. 7/8(September/October 1981); Vol. 4 no. 10 (December 1981); Vol. 5 no. 2 (February 1982
    - GLAD News (Gay and Lesbian Alliance of Greater Danbury, CT), 1988, Feb. - May; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 16)
      Vol. 6 no. 2 (Feb 1988) - Vol. 6 no. 5 (May 1988)
    - GLAD Tidings (Deleware's Lesbian & Gay News), 1983, July, Dec.; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 17)
      Vol. 2 no.7 (July 1983); Vol. 2 no. 10 (December 1983)
    - Golden Threads (Quincy, MA), 1988, July; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 18)
      Vol. 4 no. 11 (July 1988)
    - GPU News (Gay People's Union, Milwaukee, WI), 1979, Aug.; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 19)
      Vol. 8 no. 11 (August 1979)
  - Newspapers, 1979 - 1990; Subseries 2.; Oversized Boxes 19 - 26
    Newspapers produced by now defunct small presses and various lesbian, gay and women's organizations that do not include works written by Faderman.
    - Gay Life (The Midwestern Gay Weekly, Chicago, IL), 1982, Oct. - Dec; 13 issues (Box 19)
      Vol. 8 no. 16 ( October 1, 1982) - Vol. 8 no. 28/29 (December 30, 1982)
    - Gay Life (The Midwestern Gay Weekly, Chicago, IL), 1983, Jan. - Feb., July, 1985, March - April; 7 issues (Box 20)
      Vol. 8 no. 30/31 (January 13, 1983) - Vol. 8 no. 34 (February 3, 1983); Vol. 9 no. 2 (July 14, 1983); Vol. 10 no. 39 (March 28, 1985); Vol. 10 no. 43 ( April 25, 1985)
    - Gay Paper (published by the Gay Community Center of Baltimore, MD), 1983, April, 1989, Sept. - Oct., 1990, March - April; 8 issues (Box 20)
      Vol.5 no. 4(April 1983); Vol. 11 no. 1(September 1, 1989) - no. 4(October 20, 1989); no. 12(March 2, 1990); no. 14(April 6, 1990); no. 15(April 20, 1990)
    - Gay People's Chronicle (Cleveland, OH), 1985, Aug., Nov, 1986, April - Nov, 1989, April, Nov.; 10 issues (Box 21)
      Vol. 1 no.7 (August 1985), no. 10 (November 1985); Vol. 2 no. 3(April 1986) - no. 9(October 1986); Vol. 4 no. 10(April 1989); Vol. 5 no. 5(November 1989
    - GO INFO (Ottawa, Ontario), 1987, July - Sept.; 2 issues (Box 21)
      no.99(July/August 1987), no. 100(September 1987)
    - Lambda Rising BOOK REPORT (Washington, D.C.), 1989; 1 issue (Box 21)
      Vol. 2 no. 1(October/November 1989)
    - The GLC Voice (Minneapolis, MN), 1982, Nov., 1983, April, June; 4 issues (Box 21)
      Not a complete run.
    - Gaysweek, 1979, Jan. - June; 15 issues (Box 22)
      Vol. 2 no. 97(January 1, 1979) - Vol. 3 no. 114(June 24, 1979)
    - Good Times (Columbus, OH), 1984, Dec - 1985, Dec; 13 issues (Box 23)
      Vol. 1 no. 7(December 15, 1984 - no. 12(May 15, 1985); Vol. 2 no. 1(June 15, 1985) - no. 7 (December 15, 1985)
    - Good Times (Columbus, OH), 1986, Jan - 1987, Jan; 13 issues (Box 24)
      Vol.2 no. 8(January 15, 1986) - Vol. 3 no. 8 (January 15, 1987)
    - GAZE (Memphis, TN), 1979, Dec - 1982, Dec; 30 issues (Box 25)
      Vol. 1 no. 1(December 1979) - Vol. no. 1(December 1980); Vol. no. 3(February 1981) - Vol. 3 no. 12(December 1982)
    - GAZE (Memphis, TN), 1983, Jan - 1984, Nov; 21 issues (Box 26)
      Vol. 4 no. 1(June 1983) - no. 7(July/August 1983); no. 9(September 1983 - no. 12(December 1983); Vol. 5 no. 1(January 1984) - no. 10 (November 1984)
    - GAZE (Minneapolis/St. Paul and Greater Minnesota), 1987, Dec; 1 issue (Box 26)
      No. 49(December 3, 1987)
- Audio materials, 1987, Oct.; Series 4.; Box 18
  Personal interview by Faderman with Barbara Gittings, an early pioneer lesbian activist, and Mariana Romo-Carmona, a Latina lesbian from New York City, for Odd Girls and Twilight Lovers.
  - Interview with Barbara Gittings, age 55, Philadelphia, 1987, Oct. 7; 4 folders (Box 18, Folder 1 - 4)
    Gittings recalls coming out in 1950 during her freshman year in college, searching the library for any information she could find about homosexuality, turning to psychiatrists for more understanding of what it meant to be homosexual and tapping into the lesbian bar culture of New York City and Philadelphia. Gittings also touches upon her initial foree into Daughters of Bilitis, a lesbian social organization formed in San Francisco in 1955 by Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon. Gittings later established the New York City chapter of Daughters of Bilitis.
    Taped materials transferred to compact discs, which consist of one use copy (two compact discs) and one master preservation data file (two compact discs).
  - Interview with Mariana Romo-Carmona, age 35, New York City, 1987, Oct. 10; 4 folders (Box 18, Folder 5 - 8)
    Romo-Carmona, a Latina lesbian artist from New York City, discusses the alienation of lesbians of color during the 1970s and the need to become part of lesbians of color groups. Her experience as an immigrant from Chile coming out during the 1970s in New York City led her to form the Latina lesbian group Las Buenas Amigas (the Good Friends).
    Taped material transferred to compact discs which consist of one listening copy (two compact discs) and one master preservation data file (two compact discs).